welcome everyone
i'm john raviki and i'm joined i'll let
everybody introduce themselves
um i'm joined with some of the members
of
uh the meditation senate and also the
broader uh community
and what we're going to do today is
we're going to take you through
uh philosophical contemplative
companionship practice
but first of all if everybody could just
take a moment and just introduce
yourself and then i'll
lead us into the practice hello my name
is tracy williams
i'm robert gray i'm kyra kroger
so thank you uh tracy robert and jerry
for being here
so we're gonna do philosophical
contemplated companionship
what would happen is i'll be the
facilitator at this time
and what happens this the facilitator
will usually and i've already done this
will
prepare uh the other participants with a
brief
a brief background of the philosopher
whose text is going to be read
um and about the philosopher's uh
philosophy
and the philosopher's character i've
done that we're going to be reading
attention
spinoza so i filled everybody in on sort
of the background of spinoza's
philosophy
i chose uh spinoza because uh he
exemplifies the attempt to integrate uh
spirituality and science
in a profound way and his character is
very exemplary
um so what we're going to do is
explain to you the overall agenda we're
going to first begin
by taking a moment to engage our
mindfulness
abilities um all of the members
have done meditative practice and we'll
take
time of finding the core four finding
your center
root flow and focus uh and then we'll
come out of that
i will do what's called a slow reading
of the text from spinoza
then we will do a practice called
luminario which is a practice of
philosophical chanting
of a key passage from the text that sort
of stands out to the reader
then we will go into a practice called
precious speaking this is where
each one of us in turn will try
to er in a sentence or perhaps to
try to convey as deeply and expensively
as we can
what the text is evoking in us what it's
provoking in us
uh how we're trying to invoke the voice
of spinoza
we are all trying to not just speak
automatically
we're trying to avoid speaking about our
autobiography
we're trying to avoid speaking
authoritatively
what we're trying to do is to not even
get into an agreement or a disagreement
with the text we are trying to
basically make spinoza and his
philosophy as present as possible
so that we can internalize that
as we can internalize
spinoza as a sage through which we can
cultivate
wisdom and
after that uh after we've done that uh
we will do
what's called intentional uh
conversation which is a more extended
version
in which we now are more interactive
with each other
and then there'll be a stage in which we
do a takeaway which is
free form and we just discuss what came
out of the practice
all right so we're going to begin with a
few minutes of
none of us speaking i'll be silent and
people uh
all of us the four of us are going to be
taking time about
uh five minutes or so uh to find
our center our route our flow and our
focus
let's all begin please
you
um
foreign
so
you
gonna slowly come out of the mindfulness
practice
try to keep that silent open space
available to you
to bring it into listening and also when
you speak
try to speak as deeply from
the sign of depths of that space
this is spinoza from his treatise god
human
and their well-being god humans
in itself reason cannot fulfill us
and make us happy therefore we must ask
whether there is a particular kind of
knowledge
by which we could attain perfect
happiness
the kind of knowledge that leads to
happiness does not come from a source
that is distinct from happiness to the
mind
and as the mind perceives happiness
it becomes united with it
to put it another way the knowledge of
happiness
evokes love for happiness in turn
love for happiness evokes love for its
source
which we call god god cannot reveal
himself directly to us
but only through his blessing in
receiving his blessing we become united
with him
in this union does our blessings our
happiness
consist thus
i do not say that we must know god as he
is
or even that we should know him
adequately it is sufficient to know him
to some degree
in order to be united with him
even the knowledge we have of our own
bodies is very particular
we do not know our bodies just as they
are
we are totally united
with our bodies
this knowledge of god is not the
consequence of something else
but is immediate and direct
the knowledge of god is the cause of all
other knowledge
and so must be acquired by itself
alone moreover by our very nature
we are united with god so without him we
can neither exist
nor be known
this union with god is so close that it
is evident
we could not know him except
directly
for the ruminatio i have chosen as the
mind perceives happiness
it becomes united with it
i'll repeat it a few times so that we
all
can remember it as the mind perceives
happiness
it becomes united with it
as the mind perceives happiness it
becomes united with it
i will now say it and then after i say
it this time i will pass
ruminatio to tracy
as the mind perceives happiness it
becomes united
to it
as the mind precedes happiness it
becomes united
to it as the mind perceives happiness
it becomes united to it
as the mind perceives happiness it
becomes united to it
as the mind perceives happiness
it becomes united to it as the mind
perceives happiness
it becomes united to it
as the mind perceives happiness it
becomes united to it as the mind
perceives happiness
it becomes united to it
as the mind perceives happiness it
becomes united
to it as the mind perceives happiness it
to it as the mind perceives happiness
it becomes united to it as the mind
perceives happiness
it becomes united to it
as the mind perceives happiness
it becomes united to it as the mind
perceives happiness
it becomes united to it
as the mind perceives happiness it
becomes united to it
becomes united too
now we'll pause let that reverberate in
all of us
now we're going to move to precious
speaking
each one of us will try to convey as
much as we can
by saying as little as we can about what
the reading and the rumination
are evoking in us
provoking in us and how we're starting
to
invoke through it the voice
and presence of spinoza
sensing knowing happiness
as a way of knowing what's most
real
gentle serenity
calm yearning
reassuring
surprised that
this place could be gotten to and then
excited to
share it
pleased
to hear
words that touch something
deep inside about reason and happiness
sensing spinoza
in the playfulness between the reason
and the happiness
knowing the happiness
written about is accessible and
excited to seek it out
feeling the words to describe
god in the world
or in my mind
sensing the
mindset that would evoke
a line like you
can't know happiness with reason
happiness as a love
that allows me to know
putting those three things together is
insightful for me
you can't know happiness with reason
you've been going the wrong way this is
this is a better way a gentler way
and the mind feels happy in anticipation
things are simultaneously very clear
and also very different and very right
all at the same time
i feel an unusual experience of
happiness
feeling deep into my body
mind the world
the way they're joined together
i feel a strange oneness at
present
feels very very ancient and very modern
but not quite as modern as as today
maybe
i feel very connected
to this experience in this moment
so we'll now move to the intentional
conversation
in which we will continue the precious
speaking
extend it now there's a musicality that
is growing up between us
and we will now try to share it in
concert together
so
the way spinoza is trying to get us
to see
way we're united with our bodies is the
way
we're united to what's most real
is both a simple thing to say but i find
it
a profound thing to try and realize
but i'm hearing from each one of you
it's almost like a musical note that's
allowing me to get a sense of what
that's like
i'm feeling the
imminence of something
extremely precious
more accessible than i ever thought it
was before
i must get a sense that there was like
some self-discovery
that spinoza noticed in himself over
time like not
not days but like years maybe and there
was this like not an epiphany but almost
like a
like a underneath an epiphany or
something like that
i'm noticing the
reading the phrase that we did the that
we went over
the words perceive and united are
popping out in a much more vivid
and um
real way and
having a sense of the perception of
spinoza and of each of you
at the same time
yeah i want to pick up on that that that
that that weird
and wonderful interpenetration of like
the way i feel like spinoza is sort of
here between us in this interesting way
um and i like the way rob
picked up on like there's there seems to
be almost
for me a similarity between how he's
developing
here and and and robert's sense of how
he sort of
you can sense how he developed in his
thinking i i feel that there's
there's a connection there
i'm feeling a terrific gentleness
in his words we read very little
but it's so the mind
usually so chaotic
feels that it's it's in the right place
at the moment with
the four of us
yes it feels very
comfortable
it's almost like there's this space that
that spinoza had that that
he gave to us and now we're all kind of
in it
together appreciating
like not only him but us and even the
moment
itself
i'm noticing almost like a sense of
someone sitting next to me right now in
the
in this space and i can't tell if it's
one of you
or him
um and and this
and it's there's a a nervousness
a an unsure like a like a
what's what's happening like i'm i'm not
sure what's happening
and yeah that's
it's it's unsettling and yet exciting at
the same time
it is i think um
that beautiful imagery that robert just
gave us
about spinoza's space and our space and
and the co-spatiality of those spaces
and then that made me think spinoza's
trying to get us to understand
knowing as this kind of unification
and we're doing it we're exemplifying it
and we're exemplifying
him in exemplifying it it's it is
exciting and it's
like you said it's it's strange but it's
a good strange
i share the good strange feeling too
there's a sort of delighted nervousness
and i'm feeling very reluctant to start
to intellectualize the other things i
heard i'm feeling it more inside my body
as a centering of the directness
of knowing god and i don't want to start
going up here and analyzing it yet it's
it's
it's um it it tastes nice you know
it feels gentle it feels like a
warm sweater it's like oh my god this is
nice
it is like a like you're at a
destination but you're also on a journey
and you don't want to really
be at the destination because the
journey is is the better part
but yeah there's there's still a clarity
to that destination
that he kind of put in front of us
john as you were speaking the last time
i had this word come into my head
very loudly which was like a seance
and and then how tracy what you said
about
not wanting to intellectualize it
because i could see the part of my brain
that wants to do that
and like just trying to stay with
the experience and
they just and also marveling at
what's possible just with the medium
that we're using of the technology and
how this is coming about
and what what it's creating
yeah i don't i don't mind the sounds
metaphor
as long as we strip away
yes but i mean
it strikes me that we're all doing what
spinoza said when we
when we truly experience happiness and
i'm getting a sense of how it's distinct
from pleasure
we are immediately seeking to unite
with the source of that happiness
and and that and that movement is
supposed to be something profound
about us it's supposed to somehow reveal
god to us what's ultimately real
yeah this must be why i'm feeling so
comfortable with it because it's a
it's a it's a feeling of
and i'm losing speech because i just
like the feeling so much you don't want
to
spoil it with too many words
it may well be such a
strange experience that
the strangeness of this experience is
that it feels so comfortable
it doesn't feel alien or or as it
doesn't feel
awful it feels strange lovely
it is near a very terrifying place
because there is a lot of uncertainty
probably in all of us right right now
but also
there's a lot of trust and a lot of
goodwill
and also it's kind of interesting that
there's all these different
perspectives yet we're still holding
this this
perspective at the same time
i'm appreciating that sense of it like
being
this strangeness that or this
you know this strangeness that isn't
like there's an element of scary there's
an there's an edge to it
and yet there's a familiarity with it
and
i just had this thought of
wondering what
spinoza would think of what this is
creating
in the in in this space and just um
trying to think of what um
you know what words might be put to that
and i'm i'm at a loss at this moment but
maybe by the time it comes around
it'll be some thoughts
well we've now done the four rounds of
intentional conversing
and we're already if you notice we're
already sliding into
you know a more free-flowing dialogue so
now
we do that we start to do a little bit
more of what we're getting from this but
also
you know a little bit more free form
and so i'll start what i would recommend
is we first
keep the sequence going but people could
speak
a little bit more fluidly um a little
bit longer
so what what first of all i wanted to
thank everybody because it was just like
that that that i'd like that kira said
you know maybe we could call it a
secular seance or something
and you know having that and and
robert's metaphor was just for me i mean
everything was beautiful but when robert
spoke it
it was like somebody ringing a bell
everything just the
the the this like the almost the super
imposition
of what was happening between us and
then
what was what spinoza was saying and
sort of that
the hit him and us together
that space of spinoza the space between
us
i thought that was amazing and the way
it was the way we were
not just speaking what he was talking
about but we were progressively
exemplifying it we were
enacting it now when you go back i think
about what will happen to me when i go
back and read that passage now
like that passage is just gonna sing to
me it already was a meaningful passage
to me that's why i chose it
but now i i i fully expect i think it's
very
very plausible prediction that when i
read it again i mean i'm gonna
feel this i'm going to feel the concert
of intelligibility we made together
i'm going to feel that presence of
spinoza so i have a i i'm wondering
um about what that would mean to you
guys because i see how this practice
would help me to internalize the stage
how it would help me to
cultivate wisdom absolutely
yeah absolutely yeah
the the thought that's coming to mind at
the moment
is um like
being able to you know i haven't read
spinoza
but now i want to and like and going
back and reading this
and like
having you guys all could like come into
the room as i
as i'm reading you know not just spinoza
coming into the room but you guys coming
into the room and
it evoking something like i you know
that line that we repeated
there's there's no way that i'll ever be
able to read that without just having
kind of a
whoa
this must be the difference between
happiness and pleasure
yes yeah yeah this is um
pleasure that pleasure is not this is
not pleasure this is
this is a feeling of happiness which is
the strangeness of it
yes and uh
the direct experience of god is the one
that keeps
replaying in my mind we can only
experience god
directly partially because i don't know
what it means yet
and i want to i'm very curious to know
more about
what he meant by that and how one could
probably
maybe experience that
the thing that's provocative for me
about that and we all picked up on it as
we should have
is you know the the initial line that he
starts with about
you know how reason can't bring about i
mean
so the thing is spinoza is what is maybe
the most rational
he's considered one of the great
rationalists meeting him is like reading
these very complex logically tight
arguments
and yet he starts off this passage by
saying that
like there's something going on here he
wants to take us beyond
argumentation to he's going to he's
using argumentation in the passage
but he wants to take us beyond it and
there was something
and there's something like really
interesting about that
to me um because i'm thinking like the
way tracy has seen
happiness is something beyond pleasure
there there's this state beyond
argumentative reason
that's analogous to how happiness is
beyond pleasure
is that making any sense to you guys are
you getting a sense of what
because i i that's what i'm i'm feeling
spinoza's
trying to lead me too
feels like he's feeling it in his
neurons he's not thinking it in his
words
go ahead tracy i agree if what you just
said he's
feeling it in his neurons that that
makes perfect sense
and and maybe that's the effect that the
text has
is having on me i'm feeling it more than
thinking it
when john when you first read that line
of that you know
you can't get to happiness through
reason like i felt this
sense of relief like a tremendous
sense of relief and then just as we've
been talking here in this moment the
word embodied
kept coming into mind which is
you know instead of spending all of the
time in my
in my head in the mind being able to be
in the body in the heart and it was
almost like
being given permission that that line
like gave me a permission of something
that just
like created this relief flood through
my system well see that's one of the
deep differences between spinoza and
descartes
descartes gives us the modern separation
of mind and body and spinoza
consistently argues that mind
and body are two different aspects of
the same thing
i felt as a sense of very sweet relief
um when i heard that reason was not
the um the sort of the
the ultimate solution
and i also felt that
it's as kind of what kira was just
saying that
it's like oh thank god i don't have to
do all this
head work so much i can just go back in
here
and feel and be direct have these
not have but just be directly experience
body god mind
without having to because intellectual
um
reason is it can sometimes make my brain
bleed
i almost feel like i'm on a bicycle and
it's like i could go left
towards pure rationality and romanticism
and abstraction but spinoza takes me
sharp right
into the full human being and into
a rediscovery as well as an awareness
of of himself and his his world or
something like that
so so from that's that
that for me was the challenge when i
read the ethics because like reading in
the ethics is like reading euclid's
geometry it's
but the thing is if you just read it in
that headspace you don't get spinoza
like you don't you have to i almost want
to say you have to you have to read it
viscerally
i mean i have to randomly have came up
with philosophical contemplative
companionship and that gives me a
chance to give him credit right now
thank you right um
he talks about you're not you're not
speaking about
the text or thinking about it you're
speaking it and
thinking it right you're like in this
notion of embodying it
and if you'll allow me in neologism
you're in minding it
as well yeah right right and and
it's only when you do that you sort of
go beyond the argument to
like this other thing um it's really
it's a very powerful experience
it's the sense of experiencing it and
going back to what we were talking about
a moment ago about like
feeling it in the neurons like i'm
actually having this sensation of like
a tingling in my fingers and and
this sense of like and i had this moment
of
like i guess a voice saying
we get we get to be part of this process
too
like it's like the the the mental
neurons always
always get all the attention and all
that and
and you know they're always doing all
the work and like that the rest of the
body was like okay we get to participate
in this too
i think that i think that might have
been where the relief came from
was yeah
so i'm feeling a tremendous concern for
humanity
from the passage that you read a warmth
and a love of humanity
from him i think you're starting to get
the answer to your question
about what it means to know god directly
okay
really yeah because that he said he's
maybe he talks about the the you know
the you you know god the way the
mind knows the body and it's a
relationship of loving
it's almost like this god well i'm just
going to say
it's a it's a loving that keeps you
moving towards the source the grounding
are you guys you know i was gonna say it
almost reminds me of this positive
feedback loop
where he's just once you get caught into
the momentum of
it then it carries you at this new
order of magnitude up up up you know
that's pretty cool um
i'm just reminded of
story i read once and somebody talking
about having like a love affair with
the millions of cells in their body
and and just and and knowing god in that
way of like
that you know it's like just having a
deep sense of appreciation
for the you know this the
body and the organism and like every
piece of it
that works and like how every one of us
in humanity
is needed to make things to make things
work
wow that's very interesting uh first
look good enough what a great name by
the way
and the secret the secret depths of
nature actually propose
and i think she's very much in the
tradition of spinoza she
proposes exactly that she proposes that
sense of sacredness as
she calls it transcendence into rather
than transcendence above
it's really cool so i i would like to
propose i know we could do this forever
but i would like to propose we now move
to sort of a second stage of the
takeaway
and offer some reflections on the
process
like about the process of
uh philosophical contemplative
companionship i wish
i i was talking to mark about this all
right to breck
i mean it's his name and so we have to
use it but i i actually like the term
philosophical fellowship
better philosophical fellowship so
so with due regard and i've given him
appropriate credit and citation
i'm gonna now switch to saying that what
did you do what do you guys
what do you think about this process of
philosophical fellowship
this is incredibly precious this is an
absolutely gorgeous stunning beautiful
wonderful process reading is such a
lonely affair most of the time
and to have this is you know
incredibly beautiful i feel
when you asked that question i
immediately had this image
of like um like a
going through a funnel and like they're
you know
an incredibly narrow like a narrowing
that like
was like a spotlight that that like
created
a a very specific container
and then opened up into this
this this thing so it was almost like
the the beginning was like all four of
us
walking through like a very narrow
hallway
into a place that was the larger space
to
explore in uh that i that
they did something dif you know that did
something that i
i'm i want to do more of yeah
yeah it's it's interesting
how like i've heard i think you john
talk about if you read a book from like
hundreds of years ago it
unadimatizes your sense of time yeah
and i think like what what kira was
saying there was almost this shared
sense of of repopulation of the
normalness of time that we're all so
disconnected from
in the in the modern moment and in the
modern
digital world yeah that's an excellent
observation robert there is that
you know that sort of very different
shifting of sort of the relationship
between being in time
that's really that's a very good
observation
so we have i'm sorry but we have to move
towards wrapping this up we're trying to
keep this as succinct as possible
so that you can use it uh as an example
uh but i want to give people one more
opportunity for anything
you know anything summative or final
they'd like to share about it
i'll take my my my turn on uh the
summative thing just by
by expressing my deep thanks and
gratitude for all of you this one this
was wonderful thank you so very much
just saying the same thing the same
thing
yeah i'm feeling a gratitude for getting
to participate and an excitement to now
take this
to like now that i've had the experience
i'm like okay now i want to take and
want to show it to everybody and take
the experience to
the group and well
one more thanks to rand lahav for
bringing this and ultimately to
epicurus and the whole idea of
philosophical friendship
thank you one and all thank you thank
you